<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Enneades arithmeticæ, the numbring nines, or, Pythagoras his table extended to all whole numbers under 10000 and the numbring rods of the Right Honourable John Lord Nepeer : enlarged with 9999 fixt columns or rods, of single, double, triple, and quadruple figures, and with a new sort of double and moveable rods, for the much more sure, plain and easie performance of multiplication, division, and extraction of roots ...</title>
            <author>Napier, John, 1550-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56368</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4319</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12378870</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12378870</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60664</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56368)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60664)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 223:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Enneades arithmeticæ, the numbring nines, or, Pythagoras his table extended to all whole numbers under 10000 and the numbring rods of the Right Honourable John Lord Nepeer : enlarged with 9999 fixt columns or rods, of single, double, triple, and quadruple figures, and with a new sort of double and moveable rods, for the much more sure, plain and easie performance of multiplication, division, and extraction of roots ...</title>
                  <author>Napier, John, 1550-1617.</author>
                  <author>Pythagoras.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Moxon ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mathematics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60664:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:60664:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>ENNEADES ARITHMETICAE</hi> THE NUMBRING NINES. OR, PYTHAGORAS His TABLE Extended to All Whole Numbers under 10000. AND <hi>The Numbring RODS</hi> Of the Right Honourable JOHN LORD NEPEER, Enlarged With 9999 Fixt Columns or Rods, of Single, Double, Triple and Quadruple Figures, and With a New Sort of Double and Move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Rods, for the much more ſure, plain and Eaſie performance of <hi>Multiplication, Diviſion,</hi> and <hi>Extraction of Roots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Whole being very Uſeful for moſt Perſons, of whatſoever Calling and Employment, in all Arts and Sciences.</p>
            <p>All having frequent Occaſions of <hi>Accompts, Numbring, Meaſuring, Surveying, Gauging, Weighing, Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating, &amp;c.</hi> The Devine Wiſdom having from the Beginning <hi>Diſpoſed all things in Meaſure, Number and Weight,</hi> Sap. 11. 21</p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed for <hi>Joſeph Moxon,</hi> at the Sign of <hi>Atlas</hi> in <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate-ſtreet.</hi> Where alſo theſe Numbring Rods, (c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly Call'd <hi>Napiers Bones)</hi> are made and Sold. 1684.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60664:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60664:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe End and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Enſuing Table will be the better underſtood, if ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in Brief, by way of Preface, be premiſed concerning theſe Three Points. Firſt, the <hi>Table of Pythagoras;</hi> Secondly, <hi>the Extenſions of the ſame;</hi> and Thirdly, <hi>the Numbring Rods.</hi> Wherefore be pleaſed to peruſe the following Preamble concerning the ſaid Points; The Reading whereof will not Coſt thee much above an Hour or Two. But Firſt, vouchſafe to hear, what is meant by the New Title of <hi>Enneades Arithmeticae,</hi> or <hi>Numbring Nines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole following Table containing Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually all the whole Numbers from 1. to 9999<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Incluſive, Viz. 9. of One ſingle Figure, 90 of Two Figures; 900 of Three Figures; And 9000 of four Figures: Again, every one of the ſaid whole Numbers (multiplied ſeverally by all the 9 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nites, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.) making ſo many <hi>Columns,</hi> as there are <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital Numbers,</hi> to wit, 9999. each Column, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting
<pb facs="tcp:60664:3"/>
of 9 diſtinct Numbers, and theſe 9 Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers being the products of 9 diſtinct <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nits, I think we may with good Reaſon call the ſaid Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumns (yea and the Numbring Rods alſo; For in effect they are the ſame thing) by the Name of <hi>Enneades Arithmeticae,</hi> that is, the numbring Nines, or more expreſſively, the numbring Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities. For the Greek word Ἐννεας being a Nown Subſtantive, ſignifies properly the Number of nine in <hi>abſtracto,</hi> which may as well be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Ninitie, as Ἐνας ſignifying the Number of One in <hi>abſtracto,</hi> is interpreted, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifying the Number of Three in <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracto,</hi> is Tranſlated Trinity. But though there be but Nine Cells expreſt in every Rod, yet one other Negative Cell of Cyphers is ever to be underſtood, which if you pleaſe, may be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently inſinuated by putting ſo many Points over the <hi>Vertical Cell,</hi> as there are Figures in the <hi>Vertical;</hi> ſee Figure 10. whoſe <hi>Vertical</hi> is 1̇ 2̇ 3̇ 4̇ and may be pointed, as you ſee here, to inſinuate a Suppoſed Cell of Cyphers.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60664:3"/>
            <head>Concerning the Table of PYTHAGORAS.</head>
            <p>THE known Arithmetical Table, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> (ſuch as you ſee expreſſed in Figure 1.) is not only an eaſie and ſure Rule to <hi>multiply</hi> and <hi>divide</hi> by, but is alſo thoſe very Operations themſelves, <hi>Multiplication and Diviſion,</hi> done to your Hands, and known by inſpection, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending three diſtinct Numbers, proper to them both, <hi>viz. Multiplicand, Multiplier</hi> and <hi>Product,</hi> proper to Multiplication, <hi>Dividend, Diviſor</hi> and <hi>Quotient,</hi> proper to Diviſion. For if you take any one of the Numbers, Seated in their ſeveral Cells between A and B. for a multiplicand; for example 8. and another Number of thoſe that are Seated in their ſeveral Cells between A and C for a <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplier,</hi> for example 7. in the Angle of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſe. you will find the Number 56. the juſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of 8 <hi>multiplyed</hi> by 7. Again, the ſaid <hi>Product,</hi> 56. is alſo a <hi>Dividend,</hi> whoſe <hi>Diviſor</hi> is 8 in the higheſt Cell, above the <hi>Dividend</hi> and <hi>Quotient</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 7 in the 7th. Lateral Cell, over againſt the <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend,</hi> the better to diſtinguiſh the 9 Units, Figures, Numbers and Cells Seated between A and B<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from the like Seated between A and C. call th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> firſt Capital Units, Figures, Numbers, Cells, as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60664:4"/>
being placed in the Head of the Table: but the two Lying between A and C call <hi>Lateral,</hi> as occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pying the ſide of the Table on the left Hand.</p>
            <p>Every Capital number in the <hi>Pythagorean</hi> Table hath under it 8 other numbers lodged in 8 ſeveral quadrats or Cells, as you may ſee in Figure 1. all which 9 numbers make a kind of a little ſtreight Column, parallel to the ſide A C or B D. The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumns are 9 anſwerable to the 9 <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nits</hi> or <hi>Capital Numbers</hi> in the Head of the Table. But obſerve alſo, that there are other 9 <hi>Tranſverſe Columns,</hi> parallel to the ſide A B. or C D. which croſs the former at Right Angels, and meet one another in a common Cell, ever containing a perfect <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>drat Number,</hi> whoſe Root appears in the Heads of the two Meeting Columns: For Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the <hi>Column</hi> of 8 Capital meets with the <hi>Tranſverſe Col.</hi> of 8 Lateral in the Cell of 64. a ſquare Number. So 9 Capital Meets with 9 La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral in the Cell of 81. a ſquare Number, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But what is worthy of Obſervation, theſe two diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſorts of Columns, <hi>Capital and Tranſverſe,</hi> though moſt croſs one to another, do moſt pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually agree in all their Numbers, without any difference, as is manifeſt to the Eye.</p>
            <p>There are yet many things more, very Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the <hi>Pythagorean</hi> Table. The firſt is that not only the 9 Units, are <hi>multiplicand and Diviſors</hi> in it, but Tens, Hundreds, Thouſands, 10000ds, 100000. 1000000<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10000000 and 100000000. in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60664:4"/>
great variety, and all actually and orderly Tabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, ſhewing at the ſame time, their true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and Dividends, with <hi>multiplyers, Diviſors,</hi> and <hi>Quotients.</hi> As for <hi>Tens</hi> you ſee 12 Tabuated on the 1. and 2 <hi>Col.</hi> Then 23. 34. 45. 56 67. 78. 89. each number Tabulated on two Contiguous Columns. <hi>As for Hundreds,</hi> you ſee 123. Tabulated on the firſt 3 <hi>Col.</hi> Then 234 345. 456. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As <hi>for Thouſands,</hi> you have 1234. Tabulated on the four firſt <hi>Col.</hi> Then 2345. 3456. 4567. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he reſt, till you come to 123456789. a <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicand</hi> or <hi>Diviſor</hi> of all the <hi>Capital <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nits,</hi> of the Table, whoſe <hi>multiplyer</hi> is one (or more, as you pleaſe) of the Lateral Units, and the <hi>Product</hi> is the Tranſverſe Column of that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit,</hi> which you chooſe for <hi>multiplyer</hi> to be counted from the Right Hand to the left. For example, if you <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply</hi> 123456˙789 by 2. the product will be the ſecond tranſverſe col. gathered from the right hand to the left, <hi>viz.</hi> 246913˙578. If you mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply it by 9. the product will be the 9th. tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe column, <hi>viz.</hi> 1111111˙101<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing very obſervable is, that if you turn <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his Table in ſuch manner, that all the Numbers remain unchang'd in their cells, and yet the Figures 9. 8. 7. 6. 5. 4. 3. 2. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying between C<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and A. become <hi>Vertical,</hi> which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60664:5"/>
before were <hi>Lateral,</hi> and 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. lying between A. and B. <hi>become Lateral,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were <hi>Vertical,</hi> you may find another great Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of <hi>Multipliers, Diviſors, Products, Dividends</hi> and <hi>Quotients,</hi> and of greater Numbers than before, all differing from the former, and all Tabulated on contiguous columns. As for tens, you ſee 98 Tabulated on the two laſt tranſverſe columns, then 87. 76. 65 <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As for Hundreds, you have 987 876. 765. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſo for the reſt, till you come to 987654321 a Multiplicand or Diviſor made of all the Lateral unites from C. to A. which Number multiplied by 2. will have for product 1˙975308˙642. to be found in the <hi>ſecond Capital Column,</hi> and gathered thence from the right Hand to the left. If you multiply it by 9. the <hi>capital Column</hi> of 9 will ſhew the product 8˙888888˙889.</p>
            <p>The third obſervable thing is, That whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever under-cell of any Column, hath more fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures or places in it, than are in the capital cell of that Column, then infallibly the Figure which is outmoſt on the left ſide of that under-cel; is to be added to the next Figure of another Column, if another Column be Tabulated by it on the left Hand. This Addition may be called <hi>Collateral,</hi> becauſe it adds together two Figures on the ſides of two Neigbouring Columns, and makes but one Number of them both. If the two Figures ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60664:5"/>
ſhould make 10. then put down a cypher, and carry one to the next Number on the left Hand: If they make more then 10, put down the ſurplus and carry one. Take this example of <hi>Collateral</hi> Addition. If you Tabulate 12. with two Rods or Columns, <hi>viz.</hi> the column of 1 and the column of 2. in the 2d. Cell of both Rods together, is 24. in the 3d. Cell is 36. in the 4th. Cell is 48. but in the 5th. Cell is 510. which make not five Hundred and 10. but 60 only, becauſe 1 and 5 (the Neighbouring Figures of 2 Columns) are to be added into one number 6, by reaſon that the 5th. Cell of the Column 2 hath 10. in it, a Figure more than in the Capital of the Column two. This Rule then is Univerſal, whatſoever under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of any column hath more Figures in it than are in the capital number of that column, there muſt be collateral Addition, if any other column be Tabulated on the Left Hand with it. Note that this Rule holds good, not only in columns of ſingle Units, but of Tens, 100ds. 1000ds. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 4th. Obſervable thing is, and of cheif mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that all and every column, <hi>Ennead,</hi> or Rod (Synomical words in the preſent matter) not only of <hi>Pythag.</hi> his Table, but of all following Tables to 9999 and much more, is ſingularly uſeful both in <hi>Diviſion</hi> and <hi>multiplication</hi> though the Column be never ſo little (except the Column of 1 the firſt Unit, which in Rigour neither devides nor multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plys any Number) and the <hi>Dividend</hi> and <hi>multiplyer</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60664:6"/>
never ſo great. For in Diviſion it performes the work, or gives the <hi>Quotient,</hi> by meer Subſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of its own Numbers out of the <hi>Dividend:</hi> and in <hi>multiplication</hi> it gives the Product, by ſetting down in due order its own numbers, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards adding them into one Sum. For example, take the Column 25 and divide by it 7896525 the Quotient will be 315861. and the work ended will appear as underneath <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="math">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> where note that the Numbers 75. 25. 125. 200. 150. 25. all marked with this mark-are taken out of the cells of the column 25. to be ſubſtracted out of the <hi>partial Dividends:</hi> 75. is taken out of the third cell, and gives you 3. to beſet in the <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient;</hi> 25 is taken out of the 1 cell, and gives one for the <hi>Quotient,</hi> and ſo of the reſt, the Number ſhewing its cell, and the cell the <hi>Quotient.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60664:6"/>
take the column 25. for a <hi>Multiplicand.</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ultiply it by 315861. the <hi>product</hi> will be 7896525, which before was the Dividend. The Operation ended, will appear, as underneath at <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="math">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>, Where note, that the Numbers 25. 150. 200. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 25. 25. and 75. are all taken out of the cells of the column 25. to be placed as you ſee, and added in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one ſum for product of Multiplication. Here alſo you may obſerve, that the ſelf-ſame cells or Numbers are added together in <hi>Multiplication,</hi> which were ſubſtracted in <hi>Diviſion,</hi> only their Order inverted: what was firſt ſubſtracted in <hi>Diviſion,</hi> is laſt taken and added in <hi>Multiplication,</hi> which always happens when the <hi>Diviſor</hi> and <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ient</hi> become <hi>Multiplicand</hi> and <hi>Multiplier</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eproduce the <hi>Dividend</hi> as <hi>Product</hi> of <hi>Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fifth thing obſerveable is, That every <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nnead</hi> or column, be it never ſo little or great,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60664:7"/>
that is, of one, or more, or many Figures in its <hi>Capital Cell)</hi> by multiplying its Capital Number with 45. will produce a ſum equal to all the Figures, as they ſtand in that col. added into one ſum. For example, take the col. of 6. and multiply 61. by 45. the product will be 2745. which is juſt the ſum of all the column added together, as appears in the margent <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <table>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>61</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>122</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>183</cell>
                              </row>
                           </table>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <table>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>244</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>305</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>366</cell>
                              </row>
                           </table>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <table>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>427</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>488</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>549</cell>
                              </row>
                           </table>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="total">
                        <cell>2745</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </note>. By this means you may exam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne any col. whether it be right or wrong.</p>
            <p>Add unto the former or fifth Obſervation an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, not much unlike, to be ſeen <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="math">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> in this little Table of <hi>Roots, ſquares</hi> and <hi>cubes,</hi> or rather of the ending Figures or Units of all Roots, Squares and Cubes whatſoever; where you ſee the ſum of each co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumn by Addition, to be ſeverally 45.
<table>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="sup">1</hi>R</cell>
                     <cell>ſq.</cell>
                     <cell>cub.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="total">
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                  </row>
               </table> The <hi>firſt Column</hi> is of the firſt ten Roots, from 0 to 9 incluſive, but all following Roots have the ſame ending Figures, and in the ſame order, as in the firſt column. <hi>The ſecond Column</hi> is of the firſt ten ending Figures of Squares; the firſt ten Squares, and all the following Squares have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60664:7"/>
the ſame ending Figures, and in the ſame Order as in the ſecond column. <hi>The third Column</hi> is of the firſt ten ending Figures of the firſt ten Cubes, and all the following Cubes have the ſame end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Figures, and in the ſame order as in the third column. By the ending Figure of any Root, you may know the ending figure both of the ſquare and cube by this Table: in which the <hi>ſquare</hi> and <hi>cube</hi> ſtand right over againſt the <hi>Roots.</hi> Hence may you know, whether a Table of Roots, ſquares and cubes be well made or no: for if any ten ending <hi>Roots,</hi> or <hi>Squares,</hi> or <hi>Cubes</hi> lying next one under another do not make the ſum 45, or that the ſquares and cubes do not anſwer the roots, as in this Table, there muſt neceſſarily be an Errour committed.</p>
            <p>The 6th. thing very remarkable, and indeed ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable is, that <hi>multiplication and Diviſion</hi> being two very diſtinct and different Operations, yet they ſo inſeparably and eſſentially accompany one another, that the one, for example, <hi>Multiplication</hi> can never be wrought or Finiſhed by its proper Rules, but that <hi>Diviſion</hi> at the ſame time ſhall be given you without working by any Rules of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: yea, when the Operator did neither intend Diviſion, nor ſo much as think of it. That they are two different Operations, it is clear. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Multiplication,</hi> by two Numbers given <hi>(multiplicand and multiplier)</hi> ſeeks a third, <hi>Viz,</hi> the <hi>Factum or Product:</hi> But <hi>Diviſion</hi> by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60664:8"/>
two Numbers given, different from thoſe of <hi>Multiplication, (Diviſor and Dividend)</hi> ſeeks a third, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Quotient,</hi> different from the product of multiplication.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Multiplication</hi> begins its work with the leaſt figure, and Ends it with the greateſt: but <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> quite contrary, begins with the greateſt and Ends with the leaſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Multiplication</hi> requires <hi>Addition</hi> only, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Subſtraction:</hi> But <hi>Diviſion</hi> requires <hi>Subſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> only, without <hi>Addition.</hi> Notwithſtanding theſe differences of the two Operations, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to work a <hi>Multiplication</hi> but a <hi>Diviſion</hi> will be at the ſame inſtant given you, without working or dividing. So is it alſo impoſſible to work a <hi>Diviſion</hi> but a <hi>Multiplication</hi> ſhall be given you without working or multiplying. And the reaſon is manifeſt, becauſe the ſelf ſame three Numbers which conſtitute the Eſſence of <hi>Multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> conſtitute alſo the Eſſence of <hi>Diviſion,</hi> though under different denominations. The three Numbers in Multiplication are called <hi>Multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cand, Multiplyer</hi> and <hi>Product.</hi> In <hi>Diviſion, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſor, Quotient</hi> and <hi>Dividend.</hi> And obſerve, that by how much a <hi>Multiplcand</hi> exceeds or comes ſhort of his <hi>Multiplyer,</hi> by ſo much the <hi>Diviſor</hi> will exceed or come ſhort of his <hi>Quotient.</hi> The <hi>Product of Multiplication</hi> is ever equal to the <hi>Dividend in Diviſion.</hi> See the following example.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:60664:8"/>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell cols="2">
                        <hi>Multiplication wrought</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell cols="2">
                        <hi>Diviſion Given</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Multiplicand</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>144</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Diviſor</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>144</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Multiplier</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Quotient</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Product</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1728</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Dividend</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2728</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell cols="2">
                        <hi>Diviſion wrought</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell cols="2">
                        <hi>Multiplication Give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Diviſor</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>7324</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Multiplicand</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>7324</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Dividend</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4789896</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Product</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4789896</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Quotient</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>654</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Multiplier</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>654</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerve, that when in <hi>Multiplication</hi> the leſs Number is made the <hi>Muitiplicand,</hi> and the greater the <hi>Multiplier;</hi> Then in <hi>Diviſion</hi> given, the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſor</hi> is the leſs Number, and the <hi>Quotient</hi> the greater. Example.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Multiplicand</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Diviſor</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Multiplier</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>144</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Quotient</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>144</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Product</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1728</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Dividend</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1728</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>The 7th. thing obſervable is, That the third, fourth and fifth <hi>Cell</hi> of every <hi>Ennead</hi> (whether it hath one, or more or many Figures in its Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, and thoſe either pure integers or mixt with Fractions) contain three different Numbers, which are exact <hi>Roots</hi> of three <hi>exact Square Numbers,</hi> the two leſs being exactly equal to the greateſt, according to the 47. <hi>Prop. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Euclides,</hi> and the <hi>Sides</hi> or <hi>Roots</hi> making the perfecteſt ſort of right angle triangles, keeping proportion one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, as 3, 4 and 5. and having conſtantly theſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60664:9"/>
Angles <hi>proxime</hi> 90. 53. 8. and 36. 52. For ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample, take the Rod of 4. whoſe <hi>third, four<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and fifth Cells</hi> contain theſe three Numbers 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 16. and 20. the ſides of a right Angle triangle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and true <hi>Roots</hi> of theſe three ſquare Numbers 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 256 and 400. Now the two leſs ſquares <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> added together, make exactly 400. <hi>the greate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſquare of the greateſt root.</hi> Other right ang. Triang. that have not the ſaid proportion of Sides, and aforeſaid Angles, muſt neceſſarily have one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more defective Roots for their Sides, which will either come ſhort or overſhoot the truth, when we endeavor to ſquare the unſquareable Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
            <p>The eighth Point obſervable is, that though ſome Columns or Enneads refuſe all <hi>Collateral</hi> Addition, (becauſe they have no more Figures in the 8. under cells, than in the Vertical) yet others far more in Number require it. For in the whole following Table of Columns, from 1. to 9999. there are only 127. that refuſe collat. addition whereas 9872 require it, in one or more of their under cells. In the ſingle Columns of the 9 Units, only the firſt or column of 1. refuſeth Collat. Add. In the double columns of Tens, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the two firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> column 10 and 11. In the triple columns of Hundreds, only the twelve firſt, that is, all from column 100 to 111 <hi>incluſive.</hi> In the Quadruple columns of Thouſands, only the firſt 112 Columns, that is, all from column 1000
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60664:9"/>
to Col. 1111 incluſive; All which 127 Columns or bones are void of all collat. add. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the 8 Under cells in them are marked with Stars, as Signes of non-addition. Note, that no Vertical cells have any collat add. nor ſtars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. Note alſo, that no <hi>Ennead,</hi> be it never ſo great, or have many Figures in the Vertical cell, can have any collat. add. in any one Under cell, if the two firſt Figures of the Vertical begin with 10 or with theſe three 110 or theſe four 1110 <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Though all the following Figures be never ſo great, as 9999 in <hi>infinitum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ninth thing Obſervable is, that by how much any <hi>Ennead</hi> contains more Figures in its Vertical cell, by ſo much is it the better to multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly and divide by, ſince it takes away all <hi>collat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dd.</hi> the chief trouble in gathering the products <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n multiplication, and finding readily the <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ients</hi> in <hi>Diviſion.</hi> For example, if you turn all the Vertical Units of <hi>Pytha.</hi> Table into one Sum, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9. and multiply it ſeverally by 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 4. <hi>&amp;c,</hi> it would make an <hi>Ennead</hi> ſuch, as you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee expreſt in Figure 13. far different from Figure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. the Table of <hi>Pytha.</hi> whoſe <hi>collat. add.</hi> it wholy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>akes away, and yet in ſubſtance is the ſame with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Table.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oncerning the Extenſions of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his Table.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Extenſions</hi> of the <hi>Pytha.</hi> Table may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inguiſhed into two ſorts, the <hi>greater,</hi> and the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi> The greater extends it two ways; length <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay by <hi>Capital Numbers,</hi> and bredth way with as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60664:10"/>
many <hi>lateral Numbers:</hi> The leſs extends it onl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> length way by <hi>Capitals</hi> and not by any more La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terals, than are in <hi>Pytha.</hi> Table; which are the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Units. For example, the firſt greater Extenſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> adds to the 9 <hi>Capital</hi> Units of the Table 90 mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Capitals: that is, all the whole Numbers of tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> places between 10 and 99 incluſive<hi>:</hi> And the lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it adds to the 9 Lateral Units, <hi>viz.</hi> 90 more L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terals. As all the cells with their incloſed Num<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Pytha.</hi> T. are known to be 81. by multiplyin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the two greateſt Units, 9 Capital and 9 Lateral t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether; ſo by multiplying 99 by 99 the two gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Capital</hi> and <hi>Lateral Numbers</hi> of two places, yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will find the Cells of this firſt greater Extenſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be 9801. The firſt leſs Extenſion adds to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Capital Units (as did the firſt greater Extenſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 90 Numbers of two places from 10 to 99 incl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſive, but adds not any one Number to <hi>Pythago<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> his 9 lateral Units. The cells of this Extenſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> multiplying 99 its greateſt Capital by 9, the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Lateral,</hi> are found to be 891 which is not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 10th. part of 9801 the cells of the firſt grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Extenſion. A Table of this kind of extent, co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taining 9801 cells would be very uſeful, and be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of a Moderate largeneſs, occupying about 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 11 pages in <hi>Folio,</hi> might be eaſily made, as fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have heretofore done: Mr. <hi>Joh. Darling</hi> and othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> But in this preſent Table we forbear to place<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and all other Extenſions of the greater ſort, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> reaſon of their Vaſt largeneſs and labour in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and uſing them. In the following Tab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60664:10"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he one of 5 <hi>greater Extenſions,</hi> the other <hi>of</hi> 5 <hi>leſs</hi> Extenſions, you may ſee their differences and how many cells, pages and Tomes in <hi>Folio,</hi> each one would contain. But firſt obſerve, that we allow a <hi>Folium</hi> to be 14 Inches long, and 8 broad, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcinding from Margents, one page whereof will contain 112 ſquare Inches, In every page reckon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>000 cells<hi>:</hi> In every Tome a 1000 pages.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>Five greater Extenſions of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his Table:</head>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Extenſions</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1ſt.</cell>
                        <cell>2d.</cell>
                        <cell>3d.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Multiplicand</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>99.</cell>
                        <cell>999.</cell>
                        <cell>9999:</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Multiplier</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>99</cell>
                        <cell>999</cell>
                        <cell>9999.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Cells.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>9801.</cell>
                        <cell>998001.</cell>
                        <cell>99980001.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Pages.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>10 801/900</cell>
                        <cell>1108 801/900</cell>
                        <cell>111088 801/900</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Tomes.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0.</cell>
                        <cell>1 109/1000</cell>
                        <cell>111 089/1000</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <table>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Extenſions:</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="2">4 th.</cell>
                        <cell>5th.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Multiplicand</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>99˙999.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>999˙999.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Multiplier.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>99˙999.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>999˙999</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Cells.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="2">9˙999800˙001</cell>
                        <cell>99˙9998000001</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Pages.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="2">11110˙888 801/900</cell>
                        <cell>1˙111108˙888 801/900</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Tomes.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>11110.</cell>
                        <cell>889/1000</cell>
                        <cell>1111108 889/1000</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:60664:11"/>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60664:11"/>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:60664:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60664:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60664:13"/>
                     <head>Five leſs Extenſions.</head>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Extenſions</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1ſt.</cell>
                        <cell>2d.</cell>
                        <cell>3d.</cell>
                        <cell>4th.</cell>
                        <cell>5th.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Multiplicand</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>99</cell>
                        <cell>999</cell>
                        <cell>9999.</cell>
                        <cell>99999</cell>
                        <cell>999999</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Multiplier</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>9.</cell>
                        <cell>9.</cell>
                        <cell>9.</cell>
                        <cell>9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Cells</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>891</cell>
                        <cell>8991.</cell>
                        <cell>89991</cell>
                        <cell>89999</cell>
                        <cell>8999991.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Pages</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0 891/900</cell>
                        <cell>9 891/900</cell>
                        <cell>99 891/900</cell>
                        <cell>999 891/900</cell>
                        <cell>9999 891/900</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Tomes</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>1-</cell>
                        <cell>10.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe Tables, every Extenſion is expreſt by 5. oblong Quadrats, one under another. In the firſt Quadrat is the Number of the Extenſion, Firſt, ſecond or third, &amp;c. In the ſecond Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drat are two Numbers, a <hi>Multiplicand,</hi> and <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplier,</hi> being the greateſt <hi>capital Numbers;</hi> and the greateſt <hi>lateral Number</hi> of that preſent Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion. In the third Quadrat is the <hi>Product</hi> of the aboveſaid <hi>multiplicand</hi> and <hi>multiplier,</hi> or Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of cells of the Extenſion. In the fourth <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drat</hi> is the Number of pages in folio, which that Extenſion would make. Divide the cells by 900 and the <hi>Quotient</hi> will give the pages. In the fifth Quadrat is the Number of Tomes which that Extenſion would make. <hi>Divide the Page<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> by 1000. and the <hi>Quotient</hi> will give the Tomes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Extenſions both of the greater and leſſer ſort may be made <hi>in infinitum,</hi> though theſe two Tables exhibit only five of either ſort. It is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible to our firſt apprehenſions, what a vaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:60664:13"/>
ſpace would be taken up by a Table of the fifth greater Extenſion, wherein, as you ſee, 999˙999. <hi>capital Numbers</hi> are ſuppoſed to be multiplied by ſo many Laterals, and to produce the Number of cells 999˙998000˙001: and conſequently, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Allowances above-mentioned, pages <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1˙111108˙888 801/900, and Tomes in folio 1111˙108, each Tome having 1000 pages, and (with its cover) 3 inches in thickneſs. Theſe <hi>Tomes,</hi> if they were ſet on end, contiguous one to another in a ſtreight line, they would make a rank of books above 52 Engliſh miles long. Or if all the aforeſaid pages, their Margents cut off, ſhould be laid cloſe one to another on a plain, they would cover more than 30 ſquare Engliſh miles, or 19200 ſquare Acres.</p>
               <p>But ſetting aſide all Extenſions of the greater ſort, we will content our ſelves with the third leſs Extenſion, in which as the Table ſhews, 9999. is the <hi>greateſt capital Number (Multiplicand and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſor)</hi> and 9. the greateſt lateral Number <hi>(Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplier and Quotient.</hi> The product of cells is 89˙991. The pages in folio are 99 891/900 which ſcarce make the 10th. part of a Tome in folio. And obſerve that 9999 contains all the capitals, both of the <hi>Pythagorean Table,</hi> and of the firſt,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60664:14"/>
ſecond and third leſs Extenſions. For 9 (the Unit on the right hand) counts the 9 Units of the Pythagorean Table; the next 9 counts 90 Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of two places, from 10 to 99 excluſive, and makes the firſt Extenſion. The third 9. counts 900 num. of 3 places, from 100 to 999. and makes the 2d. Extenſion: The 4th. 9 counts 9000 num. of 4 places, from 1000 to 9999. and makes the 3d. Extenſion obſerve alſo, that the foreſaid numbers, of 990. 900. and 9000. added together make juſt the number of 9999: and being multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeverally by 9 do produce ſeverally theſe num. 81. 810. 8100. 81000. all which added together, make up the juſt num. of cells of the 3d. leſs Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion <hi>viz</hi> 8999. Obſerve laſtly, what we touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before ſpeaking of Pytha. Table, that every Capital number from 1 to 9999 being multiplied by all the 9 Units or ſingle figures, produces 9 diſtinct numbers, one greater than another, which being orderly placed and perpendicularly one under another, make a certain column, whoſe length is divided into 9 equal parts or cells, the Seats of the 9 Numbers produced, the Capital being the higheſt. Wherfore there being 9999 Capitals in this preſent Table, there muſt be alſo 9999 Columns, which in ſubſtance and in effect are the <hi>Numbring Nines, Enneads, Rods</hi> or <hi>Bones,</hi> or what elſe you pleaſe to call them: and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſingle Rods of Units (as they were firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and hitherto too commonly uſed) but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60664:14"/>
double Rods of Tens, Triple Rods of Hundreds, and quadruple Rods of Thouſands: So that whatever Operation can be performed in matter of Multiplication or Diviſion, by 1. 2. 3. or 4. of the ſingle Rods, the ſame may be performed by one Rod or column of this Table, and with far greater expedition, without any collateral Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. For here are actually Tabulated to your Hand all and every whole Number <hi>(Multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cands and Diviſors)</hi> under 10000, and ever with one column or Rod alone. Nay, it will not be hard to work by two columns of this Table at the ſame time, and then your Multiplicands and Diviſors may be any Number under 100000˙000. But let us proceed to the third point of the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring Rods.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Numbring Rods or Bones.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>rhombus</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:60664:16"/>
But here obſerve, that when any (9) hath a Star before it, and (1) carried to it, by reaſon of a Rod Tabulated on the right Hand of it, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat (9) becomes 10, and is capable of lateral addition, if another Rod follow on the left Hand. Obſerve alſo, that all theſe Enneads 1. 11. 111. 1111. 11111. and the like <hi>in infinitum,</hi> require Stars in all their undercells, unleſs when a (9) becomes 10 by (1) carried to it, as now we ſaid. Note alſo, that all leſs Numbers then theſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving equal places or Figures with them in the Vertical, require Stars in all Undercells: For example, 1111. is an Ennead of four places, and ſo is 1000, a leſs Number yet of four places; ſo is 1001. 1002. 1003. and ſo on till we come to 1110. all leſs Numbers then 1111. but all of four places, and requiring Stars in all their undercells. But whatſoever Number of four places is greater then 1111. as is 1112. 1113. 1114. and ſo on till 9999. then in fallibly it will reject the Star, and require lateral addition in one or more of the undercells. See the eighth Obſervable.</p>
               <p>Moreover, to avoid Multiplicity of Lines, as much as may be, in the Rods, I reduce 8 of thoſe lines to 2. which formerly ſeparated the 9. cells from one another, as you may ſee in Fig. 8. 9. 10. and 11. For dividing the length of the Rod into three equal parts by two lines, I place the three higheſt cells in the firſt Diviſion, three o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the ſecond, and the three laſt cells in the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60664:17"/>
laſt diviſion. See Fig. 8. 9. 10. and 11. accordin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to this Model of placing Stars before certai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> undercells, <hi>(viz.</hi> ſuch as have equal Number o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Figures with their capital cell) and dividing every Rod or column into three equal parts by two Lines; I made a Table, wherein all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital Numbers from 1. to 99 <hi>incluſive,</hi> were mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied by the 9. <hi>lateral <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nits.</hi> which Table being directly the firſt leſs Extenſion of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Table, I cauſed to be cut in braſs ſome years ago and a few Copies to be printed for my own and other Friends uſe. At that time I had in proſpect the other two leſs Extenſions (2d. and 3d. of <hi>Pyth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Table) which ſoon were compleated, and that very readily, by the help of the double Rod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (whereof I had made ſome Sets) and the Table of the 1 leſs Extenſion now mentioned: For lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one double Rod at a time to the Columns of that Table, you Tabulate any number from 100 to 9999. and ſee immediately the <hi>product of multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> in all the 9 cells. The other Numbers from 1 to 99 the Table it ſelf Tabulates and multiplies See a printed Copy of the Table, inſerted in <hi>pag.</hi> 27. As the ſingle Rods of my Lord <hi>Nepeer</hi> were cut out of the <hi>Pyth.</hi> Table, ſo both ſingle and dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Rods have been cut out of the Table of the 1 leſs Extenſion, and found by Experience of 9 or 10 years to double the uſefulneſs of the ſingle Rods For firſt they ſooner Tabulate any great number with fewer Rods. 2dly they Tabulate the ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:60664:17"/>
ſame number with great variety of Rods, differing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <hi>Specie</hi> one from another. See Fig. 12. 3dly they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake away more then the half of collateral Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions, the chief trouble of numbring Rods. 4thly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey more readily ſhew the product of multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation and Quotient of Diviſion in great numbers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd fewer Rods. Two of the double Rods reach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o any number under <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Collat. Additions</hi> 1 <hi>at the moſt</hi>
                  </note> 10˙000 three of them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny under <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Collat. Additions</hi> 2 <hi>at the moſt</hi>
                  </note> 100˙0000. Four of them to any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Collat. Additions</hi> 3 <hi>at the moſt</hi>
                  </note> 100000000. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This and more the double Rods perform by themſelves. But joyn or Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulate them with the Table of the 3d Extenſion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd they will moſt readily multiply and divide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt numbers. For one Rod and the Table reaches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Collat. Additions</hi> 1 <hi>at the moſt</hi>
                  </note> 1000˙000. Two to <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Collat. Additions</hi> 2 <hi>at the moſt</hi>
                  </note> 100000˙000. Three <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Collat. Additions</hi> 3 <hi>at the moſt</hi>
                  </note> 10˙000000000. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To uſe them with the Table of 9999 columns, it is neceſſary, that the Rods be of the ſame length with the columns,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60664:18"/>
though the ſame bredth is not preciſely required.</p>
               <p>The Rods having on them all the Capita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Numbers from 1. to 99. they will require eithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 50 thin two-faced Talleys, or 25 ſquare-ſide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Parallelopipedons of four faces. It will be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>venient to have every Rod twice over, (thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> once over will be ſufficient if your ſingle Rod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the 9 Units be twice or thrice over,) wherea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an ordinary Set of ſingle Bones muſt have eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Rod 4. 5. 6. 7. or more times over, according a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Operator deſignes the working of greater o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leſſer Numbers.</p>
               <p>Another way of ſupplying the want of mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Rods of one and the ſame Number, may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Table of 9999. Enneads, for in that Tab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are all Numbers of four places, and conſequent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> this Number 5757. Beſides, in the double Bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are all Numbers of two places, from 10. to 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>incluſive,</hi> and conſequently this Number 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wherefore in the Table and double Bones <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have 57. three times over. But ſetting aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Table, the Bone alone of 57. is in practi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> equivalent to three or more Bones of the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Number 57. for if you ſet down with your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> three times 57. thus 575757, as one Vertic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Number of one Ennead, you will know w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is the Content of every under cell by the und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cells of the Rod 57. thrice ſetting them do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> For example, the ſecond cell of 57. is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which thrice repeated, is 114. 114. 114. Or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:60664:18"/>
ſerving lateral Addition 1151514, which is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cond cell of the Ennead 575757. In this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er your Operation will be as ready, as if you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad had three diſtinct Rods of 57 a piece. There <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> yet a third way of moſt ready <hi>and clear work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g, multiplying and dividing vaſt Numbers</hi> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lf ſame Species of Figures, <hi>viz.</hi> all of Nines, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ights, or Sevens. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in what multiplicity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou pleaſe, of the ſame Figures, as 3. 4. 5. Nines, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea 10 Nines, 20 Nines, 100 Nines: And ſo of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ights, Sevens, sixes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some 5 ſpecial <hi>Enneads,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r 5 two-faced Rods (or two four-faced ſquare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ods) are required to this ſort of Operation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herein you will not be troubled, either with any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abulating of Rods, or collateral Addition. See <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Scheme of the ſaid <hi>ſpecial</hi> Rods <hi>pag. ult.</hi> Fig. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4 where obſerve that the nine ſingle Units oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>upy ſeverally nine Vertical cells, and their under-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ells to contain for the moſt part only 3 Figures, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e leading on the left Hand, another in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le, a 3d. ending on the Right Hand. Some few <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nder cells (not above 8 in 72) have 4 Figures in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem, and then the two laſt on the Right Hand are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nding Figures. The middle figure is moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, and more then it appears; For in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eration it is to be repeated, or taken ſo often o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, as there are Figures of one kind in the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Vertical, abating one: for example, Suppoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Vertical to be Ten Nines,</hi> or 9˙999999˙999. In the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60664:19"/>
2d. Cell of the ſpecial Rod (9) are theſe thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> figures 198. where (9) in the middle between (1) and (8) is truly nine times nine, that is, one nine leſs, then Ten nines in the Vertical: So that the ſaid 2d. cell 198, is in operation 19˙999999˙99<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or the Vertical multiplyed by (2) This Rule i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Univerſal, yet hath two exceptions; firſt whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any cell hath four figures in it; 2dly. when any cell hath a Star prefixt before it, according to what is aboveſaid concerning Aſterisks, then infallibly the middle figure is to abate, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one, but two of the number in the Vertical. One example will clear all. Let ten fours or 4˙444444˙444. be given for a Multiplicand, and 279 for a multiplyer, then in your ſpecial Rod of 4 Vertical, take out the ninth cell, apparently 396, but really 39999999996. the middle figure (9) requiring to be repeated nine times<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or one leſs, then the number of fours in the Vertical. Next take out the 7th cell, apparenly 3108 but really 31111111108. the middle figure (1) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring Eight repetitions, or two leſs then Ten of the Vertical, becauſe this 7th cell hath 4 fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures in it. Laſtly take our the 2d cell, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently * 888. but really * 8888888888. becauſe the middle figure (8) requires 8 repetition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (beſides the leading and ending 8) or two leſs then Ten of the Vertical, by reaſon of the Star
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60664:19"/>
prefixt before the ſecond cell. The Work end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed would appear thus in Multiplication.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Multiplicand</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4˙444444˙444</cell>
                        <cell>39999999996</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>cell. 9</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Multiplier</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rend="rightJustify">╌279</cell>
                        <cell>31111111108</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>cell. 7</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell cols="2"> </cell>
                        <cell>8888888888</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>cell. 2</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Product</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1239˙999999˙876</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Product</hi> 1239999999876 In <hi>Diviſion, Multiplicand</hi> the <hi>Diviſor, Product</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Dividend,</hi> and <hi>Multiplier</hi> the <hi>Quotient.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell cols="2"> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Dividend</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Diviſor</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4˙444444˙444)</cell>
                        <cell>1239999999876</cell>
                        <cell>(279<hi>Qu.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell rend="rightJustify">2╌</cell>
                        <cell>8888888888</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell cols="2"> </cell>
                        <cell>35111111107</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell rend="rightJustify">7╌</cell>
                        <cell>31111111108</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell cols="2"> </cell>
                        <cell>39999999996</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell rend="rightJustify">9╌</cell>
                        <cell>39999999996</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell cols="2"> </cell>
                        <cell>0000000000</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>The ſquare and cube Rod ought to be once o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er in every Set, with three or four cypher-Rods, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s you ſee expreſt in Fig. 11, All are to be ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erly placed in a neat pocket caſe, that every Rod be known what Number it hath. by a mark <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r figure, even before you take it out of the Caſe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f you pleaſe to reprint the Table of the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs Extenſion by it ſelf in a page, (with its co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umns, equal to the Columns of the great Table <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f 9999.) and give it a Varniſh to laſt the longer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou may immediately thence make Sets of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouble bones, meerly by cutting out the capital
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60664:20"/>
columns, and paſſing them on Talleys of Wood or other matter (two faced or four faced) of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſame length and bredth with the columns. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, as is aboveſaid, this little Table of the firſt leſs Extenſion, with one double Rod applied unto it at a time, performs all the whole Work of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great Table of 9999 fixt columns, only with thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſadvantage, that it will often have one col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateral Addition, whereas the great Table wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have none. Notwithſtanding the great perform<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ances of the leſs Table, the great Table hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many ſpecial uſes, for which it deſerves to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> publiſhed, eſpecially not being of any great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, nor making any great bulk. By advice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Judicious Friends, I thought good to put it fort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in a <hi>Duodecimo,</hi> as a convenient <hi>Enchiridion,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> pocket-book, every four pages containing 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> columns with their 900 cells, or every page 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> columns with 225 cells. In which caſe the Ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble alone would require 400 pages in <hi>Duodeci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> But perhaps it will be better, to contract the pag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to half the Number, <hi>viz.</hi> to 200. in this manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Let every page have five Ranks of Columns o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> under another, each Rank conſiſting of Ten C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lumns: ſo will every page contain 50 Column<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and whereſoever you open the book, the two p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges before your eyes, will ſhew you a juſt Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred of Columns. To find the Number yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeek for, more readily, you may Tack to the Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gent little outſtanding Labells, or Indexes, ſhe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60664:20"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> before you open the Book, where every 100 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd 1000 begins, ſuch as are ſeen in certain ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ount-books of Merchants. Let the Book be ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound, that whereſoever you open it, the leaves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n either ſide, may lye Flat without any upriſing; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or ſo it will be more eaſie to Contabulate the Rods with the Table, when occaſion requires. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erhaps it would be better to print it in a little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olio, for uſe at home in your Cloſet or Library; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or then every page would contain its Hundred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Columns, eaſie to be found out by their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ural order.</p>
               <p>As well the forementioned Table of 9999 fixt Columns, as the ſingle and double moveable Rods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erve equally in Decimal and common Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ick; yea in Decimal, they in a manner take away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll the trouble of Diviſion. Neither do they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e any particular Rules in operation, different <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom thoſe which have been delivered concerning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Lord N <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſingle bones, by himſelf in his <hi>Rab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ologia,</hi> by <hi>F. Andrew Taquet, Sir Jonas Moor,</hi> Mr <hi>William Leybourne</hi> and others in their Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metical Treatiſes. Wherefore I ſhall ſay no more of them but only ſhew by ſingle examples, (one of multiplication, another of Diviſion, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d of extraction of the Square Root, the 4th of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he cube Root) the ordinary uſe of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Example of Multiplication.</head>
               <p>In <hi>multiplication</hi> commonly it is beſt to Tabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate the greater Number as <hi>multiplicand</hi> when one
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60664:21"/>
is greater then the other. For example. <hi>Tabulat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 4628 to be <hi>multiplyed</hi> by 72. Place Unit unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Unit, as in the Margent <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Then for 2 (the Un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the <hi>Multiplyer)</hi> take the 2d cell of the <hi>Multi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plicand, viz.</hi> 9256. and for 7 of the multiplyer tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the 7th cell of the <hi>Multiplicand, viz.</hi> 32396, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſet both cells down, as you ſee in <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Add the tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cells together, and the total Sum or product o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> multiplication will be 333216 as you find in <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> But if you Tabulate 72 to be multiplyed by 462<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the operation will appear as in <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>In Diviſion the <hi>Diviſor is to be Tabulated;</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it much imports, for the ſpeedier diſpatch of yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> operation, that the <hi>leading Rod of the Diviſor</hi> be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great Rod or Column of the Table; a quadrupl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rather then a Triple, a Triple then a double, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> double then a ſingle, if the Number of your Di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>viſor will permit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:60664:21"/>
               <head>Example of Diviſion</head>
               <p>Let 5678556 be a <hi>Dividend,</hi> and 4628 the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſor.</hi> ſet them down as in the Margent <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> with a Semilune, for the Quotient, and Tabulate the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſor. Then enquire how often can the <hi>Diviſor</hi> 4628. be taken out of the firſt <hi>partial Dividend, viz.</hi> 5678. Only once; Therfore put 1 for Quotient in the Semilune, and Subtract 4628 out of 5678. and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere will remain 1050 the work ſtanding (if you caſh t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Figures diſpatcht) as in <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>. Next bring down 5 out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Dividend,</hi> and place it on the right Hand of the remainder, as you ſee in <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſeparated with a Comma. This done, ſeek in the cells of the Diviſor for 10505 (the next par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Dividend) or for the next leſs Number then 10505. In the 2d. cell is 9256 the next leſs. Put 2 in the Quotient, and <hi>Subtract</hi> 9256 out of 10505. and the remainder will be 1249 to which bring down the other) of the Dividend, and daſh what is diſpatcht. Then will the work ſtand, as in <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:60664:22"/>
In like manner proceed to find the 3d. and 4th. figure of the <hi>Quotient,</hi> and the work finiſhed will appear, as in <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Others daſh no figures at all, not place the Quotient on the Right Hand of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidend,</hi> but ſet every quote-figure over againſt the cell of the <hi>Diviſor</hi> from whence it was taken. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very remainder they diſtinguiſh with a colum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from the figure brought down out of the <hi>Dividend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> as you may ſee in <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> When in one Number ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> happen to be two columns, there will be a cypher in the Quotient; when 3 Commaes, then 2 Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers in the Quotient. The like Method ſerve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:60664:22"/>
wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Extraction of the Square Root,</hi> and much <hi>Fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tate</hi> the examining of the work done. If any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umber remain after Diviſion ended, it will be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Numerator</hi> of a Fraction, whoſe <hi>Denominator</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the <hi>Diviſor.</hi> When you turn Integers into a <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius of Decimals, Diviſion</hi> either ceaſes, or is eaſily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad by cutting off ſo many Figures (on the Right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>Hand) from the <hi>product of multiplication</hi> as are in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Radius,</hi> excepting one.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Example of the Square Roots Extraction</head>
               <p>The Extraction of the Square Root is very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and plain by the Table, or by the double Rod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or both of them together. Let the number given, <hi>whoſe Root you ſeek,</hi> be 70476025. Put a point un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Unit, and every A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tern Figure with a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milune after the Unit as you ſee in <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> The 4 points foretell that in the operation there will be 4 par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial <hi>Dividend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and as many Roots. Then ſeek in the cells of the Square Rod for 70 (the 1 partial Dividend) or the nearer leſs number to 70. 64 is the neareſt leſs to 70 in the 8th cell. Therefore 8 <hi>is your firſt Root</hi> to be placed in the Semilune, and 64 is to be Subtracted out of 70. The remainder will be 6 the work appearing as in <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>. For the finding the 2d. 3d. or any other Square Roots following, obſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rve theſe Rules: Firſt, bring down
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60664:23"/>
the next parttial Dividend and joyn it to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> remainder on the Right Hand.</p>
               <p>Secondly, double the <hi>Root or Roots found,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tabulate that <hi>double</hi> on the left Hand of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Square Rod or (working by the Table) carry t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Square Rod to the double in the Table.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſeek for the Number (or next leſs) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> your laſt remainder joyned to the next <hi>partial D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vidend</hi> in the cells of the Tabulated Rods and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cell</hi> wherein it is found, will give you the nex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Root.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Subtract the cells Number out of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> remainder and partial Dividend, and proceed a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before, wherefore in our preſent example to fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the 2d. Root,</p>
               <p>Firſt, bring down 47 and joyn it to 6 to make 647.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Double the Root</hi> 8 and <hi>Tabulate</hi> 16 with the Square Rod.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſeek 647 (or the nearer leſs) in the Tabulated Rods the third cell gives 489, the next leſs, which Subtracted out of 647, leaves the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder 158. The 3d. cell gives 3 for the 2d. Root: ſee the Margent <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> For the finding o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the 3d. and 4th. Root, proceed as before. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:60664:23"/>
whole Operation ended ſtands as underneath a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> or according to the Method, mentioned in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iviſion, underneath at <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> where any number re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ains after the work ended, it is the Numerator <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f a Fraction, whoſe Denominator is the double <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f all the Roots and one Unit more. But if you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſire a more exact Fraction, add to the Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ator 2. 3. or more Couples of Cyphers, and wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s before, and you will find the nearer Decimal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Example of the Cube-Roote's Extraction.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. ſet down the number (whoſe Cube-root you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ek) with a point under the Unit and every 3d.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60664:24"/>
Figure, and a Semi-Lune for the Roots, as unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neath at <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> how many points, ſo many parti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Dividends and Rootes will be in the Operatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>2ly, Seek in the Cube Rod for 94 or the neare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leſs number: In the 4th cell you find the neareſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Set down 4 for the 1 Root and Subtract 64 o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of 94, the remainder will be 30; and the work ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as in <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>For the finding of the 2d, or any other follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Root, obſerve theſe Rules.</p>
               <p>1ſt. Bring down the next partial Dividend 81<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and joyn it to the remainder 30, on the Right Hand, as in <note n="s" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>2ly, Tabulate the triple of Root or Roots found <hi>(Root</hi> 4 <hi>the triple</hi> 12) with Rod or Rods apart call them for diſtinction, <hi>Right Hand Rods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3ly. Tabulate the triple of the Sq. of the Root<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> found (Root 4 Square 16 the triple of 48) with Rod or Rods. placed on the left Hand, of the Cube Rod: call theſe left Hand Rods. Or work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Table, carry your cube-Rod to 48 in your Table.</p>
               <p>4ly, Seek for 30818 the preſent partial dividend or next leſs number, in the cells of the left Hand Rods. In the 6th cell you find 29016 the next le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> yet indeed too much, 2s will after appear. Set th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:60664:24"/>
this number down apart, and draw a line abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t as you ſee in <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> over the Unit; and above the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine place 6 the number of the cell, out of which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9016 was taken: On the left Hand of 6 place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Square of 6, <hi>viz.</hi> 36 as you ſee in <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> then take the 6th and 3d. cell (by reaſon of 36 the Square) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut of the right Hand Rods, <hi>viz.</hi> 72 and 36 and place them as you ſee in <note n="w" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> adding all the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers under the line into one Sum, <hi>viz.</hi> 33336, as you ſee in <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> which being too great to be taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut of 30818. you muſt go back and take a leſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell, then 6.</p>
               <p>Take therefore the cell 5. which hath in it the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e number 24125. write it apart with a line a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ove it, and an above line over the Unit: place 5 the cells number) and on the left Hand of 5 the he Square of 5 <hi>viz.</hi> 25 as in the margent <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake out of the right Hand Rods the 5th. and 2d. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell (by reaſon of the Square 25) <hi>viz.</hi> 60 and 24 and add them, as you ſee in <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> to make 27125 which taken out of 30818 there will remain 3693 and the work ſtand as in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60664:25"/>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> For the 3d Roo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do as you did for the 2d.</p>
               <p>1ſt, Bring down the nex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Dividend and joyn it to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> laſt remainder.</p>
               <p>2ly, Tabulate a part on the right Hand Rod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the triple of the Roots found.</p>
               <p>3ly, Tabulate the triple of the Square of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Roots on the left Hand of the Cube-Rod.</p>
               <p>4ly, Seek in the cells of the left Hand rods fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the left Hand rods for the partial Dividend.</p>
               <p>5ly, Set down apart the number required <hi>foun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and draw a line above it: above that line a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> over the Unit place the Figure of the cell take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and on the lefthand of the figure, place its ſquar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s was expreſſed as before above in the margen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>(u)</hi> the whole Operation ended, will appear brie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as in <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Note firſt, that ſcarce can you give any prece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in writing concerning Extraction of rootes, clear, but that they ſhall confound or puzzle young Student of Arithmetick, who will be ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to learn more in an Hour of a Maſter ſhewi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60664:25"/>
him the practice, than in a day or week by his own reading of precepts.</p>
               <p>2ly, note, that in Cubick Extractions it is not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to foreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e or prevent the taking of too great a number out of the <hi>left Hand and Cube-Rods.</hi> We may probably conjecture that it will happen ſo, when the number taken is almoſt as great as the partial Dividend, and yet is to be increaſed by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding 1 or 2 cells more out of the <hi>Right Hand Rods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3ly, Note, that when the capital cell of the left hand and cube-rods is greater than the partial Dividend, a <hi>Cypher</hi> is to be put in the <hi>Quotient</hi> as a <hi>Root,</hi> and the next partial dividend is to be brought down and joyned to the former.</p>
               <p>4ly, note, that if any number remain after Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, it muſt be ſet down as the Numerator of a common Fraction, whoſe Denominator is a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber made of the <hi>triple of all the</hi> rootes, and of the triple of the Square of all the rootes, and an U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. For example. The rootes being 456 the <hi>Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> would be 625177 See the Margent <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Triple of Rootes.</cell>
                           <cell>1368</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Triple of Square.</cell>
                           <cell>623808</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</cell>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Summa</cell>
                           <cell>625177</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </note> But far better it is to add to to the Numerator, or the remaining number, 3 or 4 triples of cyphers thus, 000, 000, 000. and work out by the precedent rules a clear and plain decimal Fraction.</p>
               <p>Thus much (and indeed more than I firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) concerning <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his Table, the Extenſions thereof, and the Numbring Rods.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60664:26"/>
And here I might (had I not been too long al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ready) exempliſy in a few inſtances; and there by ſhew, that whatſoever is performed by <hi>Loga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmes</hi> in Problemes of Trigonometry, <hi>Sines Tangents, Secants, Queſtions of Intereſt,</hi> &amp;c. may be alſo performed by this Table of the <hi>third leſs Extenſion,</hi> and the <hi>double Rods,</hi> or by the double Rods alone: whether with more readineſs and clearneſs, Practice and Experience muſt ſhew.</p>
               <p>What alſo can be performed by Mr. <hi>Brigges</hi>'s Table of 20 Chiliades of Logarithmes, may be done (if I miſtake not) more plainly and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily by this Table. For though it be but the half of 20 Chiliades, (it being only 10 Chiliades), yet by applying one double Rod thereunto, it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds 20 Chiliades by 980˙000 Chiliades.</p>
               <p>For Concluſion, I will here ſuggeſt certain Lines divided into certain digits, which are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly uſeful in meaſuring moſt things meaſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and make your Operation quick and plain, without trouble of diviſion, or neceſſity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing inches into other known Integers. For though you meaſure by digits only, and multiply them by one another, yet the Product of Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication immediately gives you in hundreds or thouſands, the ſuperficial or ſolid content, not only in digits, but in other known termes of Feet, Yards, Acres, Gallons, Barrels, Buſhels, &amp;c. For Wine-Gallon-digits proceed thus, Take the <hi>Cube Root</hi> of 231, (the ſolid inches in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60664:26"/>
a Wine-Gallon) which is 6, 136 <hi>vulg. Inc. proxime. Divide</hi> this Root into ten equal parts exactly, with ſubdiviſions of each part into other ten leſs parts, and you have the Wine-Gallon-digits.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You</hi> meaſure by them, for example, a cylin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drical capacity, and find the Diameter of it to be 56 digits, and height 60 digits, <hi>the area</hi> of that circle will be 24,64 ſuperficial digits, which mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied by 60 digits, produces 147.840 ſolid di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gits, whereof every thouſand is a juſt Wine-Gallon. There are therefore 147 Gallons, and 840 digits towards another thouſand or Gallon: that is above three quarts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For Beer or Ale</hi> Gallon digits, take the cube Root of 282 ſolid vulg. inches in the AleGallons, which is 6,558 <hi>proxime. Divide</hi> this Root into ten equal parts, with ſubdiviſions, as above.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Beer-barrel-digits,</hi> take the cube Root of 10152 (ſolid vulg. inc. in a Beer-barrel of 36 Gall.) which is 21,653 <hi>proxime,</hi> to be divided into ten equal parts with ſubdiviſions, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For Foot-digits</hi> take the ſquare-Root of 144 (a Foot ſquare) or cube<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Root of 1728, (a Foot ſolid) both which is 12 common inc. Divide this Root 12 into ten equal parts, with ſubdiviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; meaſure and work by them, every hundred ſquare will be a true Foot ſquare, equal to 144 common inc. and every thouſand ſolid, a Foot ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid equal to 1728 com. inc. For example, you meaſure a tetragon pyramide, whoſe one ſquare ſide is 50 Foot-digits, and height 60. The ſquare
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60664:27"/>
of 50 is 2500, and gives the area of the pyramid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at the bottom, <hi>viz.</hi> 2500 ſq. dig. or 25 ſq. Feet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> multiply the area 2500 by 20 (a 3d of the height 60) and the product will be 50000 fol. dig. that is 50 ſolid Feet, equal to 86400 ſolid common inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe 4 lines of Wine-gall. dig. Beer-gall. dig. and foot-digits, are of excellent uſe in Gauging, and meaſuring any thing by feet ſq. or ſolid, and may be conveniently cut on a Ruler, or long mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring ſtaff, hard by or on both ſides of a line of common inches, ſo that by meer inſpection you may ſee how much they differ amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and from common inches. If you deſire yard-dig. to meaſure by ſq. or cube-vards, divide 36 the ſquare Root of 1296 (a ſq. yard in common inches) and cube Root of 46656 (a yard ſol. in common inches) into ten equal parts, as in other digits above; So may you have buſhel-dig. by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding 12, 958, which is <hi>proxime</hi> the cube Root of 2176 (commonly eſteemed a ſolid buſhel in vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar inches) into 10 equal parts. For meaſuring of Land, Mr. <hi>Gunter</hi>'s Chain (of 100 links, equal to 4 perches or 66 foot in length, is very convenient. Every 10000 ſq. links is a chain ſq. or 16 perch. ſq. or the 10th. part of an Acre ſ. 100000 of links ſq. is 10 chains ſq. or 160 perches ſq. or an Acre ſq. Note 1. That when the Root is great, as 20, 30, or more vulg. inc. then you may divide it into more than 10 equal parts, as 100. 1000, &amp;c. Note 2. That in working by the aforeſaid Root-dig, the contingent Fractions will be decimal and clear.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:60664:27"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:60664:28"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Fol. 32. lin. 12. ſet them thus 72. <gap reason="math">
                  <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fol.</hi> 33 <hi>l.</hi> 21. read thus <gap reason="math">
                  <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fol.</hi> 39 <hi>l.</hi> 12. <gap reason="math">
                  <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="tetrastich">
            <pb facs="tcp:60664:28"/>
            <head>TETRASTICHON. In Enneadas Arithmeticas.</head>
            <p>COnditor Aen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>idos peperit ſibi nobile Nomen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nullum Nomen habet Conditor Enneados. Si tamen Enneados, quaeratur, quis fuit Author? Baro, Refer, Neperus, Pythagorasque fuit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Aeneid's Author is a Man much Fam'd,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Ennead's Author not ſo much as Nam'd;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But if you are askt who th' Ennead's Author was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Say Lord</hi> John Neper, <hi>and</hi> Pythagoras.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="distich">
            <head>DISTICHON. In Tabulam 10000 Enneadum.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>HAc Tabula Enneadas decies tibi Mille Miniſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pythagorae tantum priſca Tabella decem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Table gives Ten Thouſand Enneades, when <hi>Pythagora's</hi> Old Table gives but Ten.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tables">
            <pb facs="tcp:60664:29"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60664:29"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>29</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>31</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>33</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>*2</cell>
                     <cell>*4</cell>
                     <cell>*6</cell>
                     <cell>*8</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>*20</cell>
                     <cell>*22</cell>
                     <cell>*24</cell>
                     <cell>*26</cell>
                     <cell>*28</cell>
                     <cell>*30</cell>
                     <cell>*32</cell>
                     <cell>*34</cell>
                     <cell>*36</cell>
                     <cell>*38</cell>
                     <cell>*40</cell>
                     <cell>*42</cell>
                     <cell>*44</cell>
                     <cell>*46</cell>
                     <cell>*48</cell>
                     <cell>*50</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>52</cell>
                     <cell>*54</cell>
                     <cell>*56</cell>
                     <cell>*58</cell>
                     <cell>*60</cell>
                     <cell>*62</cell>
                     <cell>*64</cell>
                     <cell>*66</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>*3</cell>
                     <cell>*6</cell>
                     <cell>*9</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>*30</cell>
                     <cell>*33</cell>
                     <cell>*36</cell>
                     <cell>*39</cell>
                     <cell>*42</cell>
                     <cell>*45</cell>
                     <cell>*48</cell>
                     <cell>*51</cell>
                     <cell>*54</cell>
                     <cell>*57</cell>
                     <cell>*60</cell>
                     <cell>*63</cell>
                     <cell>*66</cell>
                     <cell>*69</cell>
                     <cell>*72</cell>
                     <cell>*75</cell>
                     <cell>*78</cell>
                     <cell>*81</cell>
                     <cell>*84</cell>
                     <cell>*87</cell>
                     <cell>*90</cell>
                     <cell>*93</cell>
                     <cell>*96</cell>
                     <cell>*99</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>*4</cell>
                     <cell>*8</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>*40</cell>
                     <cell>*44</cell>
                     <cell>*48</cell>
                     <cell>*52</cell>
                     <cell>*56</cell>
                     <cell>*60</cell>
                     <cell>*64</cell>
                     <cell>*68</cell>
                     <cell>*72</cell>
                     <cell>*76</cell>
                     <cell>*80</cell>
                     <cell>*84</cell>
                     <cell>*88</cell>
                     <cell>*92</cell>
                     <cell>*96</cell>
                     <cell>100</cell>
                     <cell>104</cell>
                     <cell>108</cell>
                     <cell>112</cell>
                     <cell>116</cell>
                     <cell>120</cell>
                     <cell>124</cell>
                     <cell>128</cell>
                     <cell>132</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>*5</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>*50</cell>
                     <cell>*55</cell>
                     <cell>*60</cell>
                     <cell>*65</cell>
                     <cell>*70</cell>
                     <cell>*75</cell>
                     <cell>*80</cell>
                     <cell>*85</cell>
                     <cell>*90</cell>
                     <cell>*95</cell>
                     <cell>100</cell>
                     <cell>105</cell>
                     <cell>110</cell>
                     <cell>115</cell>
                     <cell>120</cell>
                     <cell>125</cell>
                     <cell>130</cell>
                     <cell>135</cell>
                     <cell>140</cell>
                     <cell>145</cell>
                     <cell>150</cell>
                     <cell>155</cell>
                     <cell>160</cell>
                     <cell>165</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>*6</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                     <cell>*60</cell>
                     <cell>*66</cell>
                     <cell>*72</cell>
                     <cell>*78</cell>
                     <cell>*84</cell>
                     <cell>*90</cell>
                     <cell>*96</cell>
                     <cell>102</cell>
                     <cell>108</cell>
                     <cell>114</cell>
                     <cell>120</cell>
                     <cell>126</cell>
                     <cell>132</cell>
                     <cell>138</cell>
                     <cell>144</cell>
                     <cell>150</cell>
                     <cell>156</cell>
                     <cell>162</cell>
                     <cell>168</cell>
                     <cell>174</cell>
                     <cell>180</cell>
                     <cell>186</cell>
                     <cell>192</cell>
                     <cell>198</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>*7</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                     <cell>49</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                     <cell>*70</cell>
                     <cell>*77</cell>
                     <cell>*84</cell>
                     <cell>*91</cell>
                     <cell>*98</cell>
                     <cell>105</cell>
                     <cell>112</cell>
                     <cell>119</cell>
                     <cell>126</cell>
                     <cell>133</cell>
                     <cell>140</cell>
                     <cell>147</cell>
                     <cell>154</cell>
                     <cell>161</cell>
                     <cell>168</cell>
                     <cell>175</cell>
                     <cell>182</cell>
                     <cell>189</cell>
                     <cell>196</cell>
                     <cell>203</cell>
                     <cell>210</cell>
                     <cell>217</cell>
                     <cell>224</cell>
                     <cell>231</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>*8</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                     <cell>*80</cell>
                     <cell>*88</cell>
                     <cell>*96</cell>
                     <cell>104</cell>
                     <cell>112</cell>
                     <cell>120</cell>
                     <cell>128</cell>
                     <cell>136</cell>
                     <cell>144</cell>
                     <cell>152</cell>
                     <cell>160</cell>
                     <cell>168</cell>
                     <cell>176</cell>
                     <cell>184</cell>
                     <cell>192</cell>
                     <cell>200</cell>
                     <cell>208</cell>
                     <cell>216</cell>
                     <cell>224</cell>
                     <cell>232</cell>
                     <cell>240</cell>
                     <cell>248</cell>
                     <cell>256</cell>
                     <cell>264</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>*9</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                     <cell>81</cell>
                     <cell>*90</cell>
                     <cell>*99</cell>
                     <cell>108</cell>
                     <cell>117</cell>
                     <cell>126</cell>
                     <cell>135</cell>
                     <cell>144</cell>
                     <cell>153</cell>
                     <cell>162</cell>
                     <cell>171</cell>
                     <cell>180</cell>
                     <cell>189</cell>
                     <cell>198</cell>
                     <cell>207</cell>
                     <cell>216</cell>
                     <cell>225</cell>
                     <cell>234</cell>
                     <cell>243</cell>
                     <cell>252</cell>
                     <cell>261</cell>
                     <cell>270</cell>
                     <cell>279</cell>
                     <cell>288</cell>
                     <cell>297</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>34</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>46</cell>
                     <cell>47</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell>49</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                     <cell>52</cell>
                     <cell>53</cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                     <cell>59</cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                     <cell>61</cell>
                     <cell>62</cell>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                     <cell>65</cell>
                     <cell>66</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>*68</cell>
                     <cell>*70</cell>
                     <cell>*72</cell>
                     <cell>*74</cell>
                     <cell>*76</cell>
                     <cell>*78</cell>
                     <cell>*80</cell>
                     <cell>*82</cell>
                     <cell>*84</cell>
                     <cell>*86</cell>
                     <cell>*88</cell>
                     <cell>*90</cell>
                     <cell>*92</cell>
                     <cell>*94</cell>
                     <cell>*96</cell>
                     <cell>*98</cell>
                     <cell>100</cell>
                     <cell>102</cell>
                     <cell>104</cell>
                     <cell>106</cell>
                     <cell>108</cell>
                     <cell>110</cell>
                     <cell>112</cell>
                     <cell>114</cell>
                     <cell>116</cell>
                     <cell>118</cell>
                     <cell>120</cell>
                     <cell>122</cell>
                     <cell>124</cell>
                     <cell>126</cell>
                     <cell>128</cell>
                     <cell>130</cell>
                     <cell>132</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>102</cell>
                     <cell>105</cell>
                     <cell>108</cell>
                     <cell>111</cell>
                     <cell>114</cell>
                     <cell>117</cell>
                     <cell>120</cell>
                     <cell>123</cell>
                     <cell>126</cell>
                     <cell>129</cell>
                     <cell>132</cell>
                     <cell>135</cell>
                     <cell>138</cell>
                     <cell>141</cell>
                     <cell>144</cell>
                     <cell>147</cell>
                     <cell>150</cell>
                     <cell>153</cell>
                     <cell>156</cell>
                     <cell>159</cell>
                     <cell>162</cell>
                     <cell>165</cell>
                     <cell>168</cell>
                     <cell>171</cell>
                     <cell>174</cell>
                     <cell>177</cell>
                     <cell>180</cell>
                     <cell>183</cell>
                     <cell>186</cell>
                     <cell>189</cell>
                     <cell>192</cell>
                     <cell>195</cell>
                     <cell>198</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>136</cell>
                     <cell>140</cell>
                     <cell>144</cell>
                     <cell>148</cell>
                     <cell>152</cell>
                     <cell>156</cell>
                     <cell>160</cell>
                     <cell>164</cell>
                     <cell>168</cell>
                     <cell>172</cell>
                     <cell>176</cell>
                     <cell>180</cell>
                     <cell>184</cell>
                     <cell>188</cell>
                     <cell>192</cell>
                     <cell>196</cell>
                     <cell>200</cell>
                     <cell>204</cell>
                     <cell>208</cell>
                     <cell>212</cell>
                     <cell>216</cell>
                     <cell>220</cell>
                     <cell>224</cell>
                     <cell>228</cell>
                     <cell>232</cell>
                     <cell>236</cell>
                     <cell>240</cell>
                     <cell>244</cell>
                     <cell>248</cell>
                     <cell>252</cell>
                     <cell>256</cell>
                     <cell>260</cell>
                     <cell>264</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>170</cell>
                     <cell>175</cell>
                     <cell>180</cell>
                     <cell>185</cell>
                     <cell>190</cell>
                     <cell>195</cell>
                     <cell>200</cell>
                     <cell>205</cell>
                     <cell>210</cell>
                     <cell>215</cell>
                     <cell>220</cell>
                     <cell>225</cell>
                     <cell>230</cell>
                     <cell>235</cell>
                     <cell>240</cell>
                     <cell>245</cell>
                     <cell>250</cell>
                     <cell>255</cell>
                     <cell>260</cell>
                     <cell>265</cell>
                     <cell>270</cell>
                     <cell>275</cell>
                     <cell>280</cell>
                     <cell>285</cell>
                     <cell>290</cell>
                     <cell>295</cell>
                     <cell>300</cell>
                     <cell>305</cell>
                     <cell>310</cell>
                     <cell>315</cell>
                     <cell>320</cell>
                     <cell>325</cell>
                     <cell>330</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>204</cell>
                     <cell>210</cell>
                     <cell>216</cell>
                     <cell>222</cell>
                     <cell>228</cell>
                     <cell>234</cell>
                     <cell>240</cell>
                     <cell>246</cell>
                     <cell>252</cell>
                     <cell>258</cell>
                     <cell>264</cell>
                     <cell>270</cell>
                     <cell>276</cell>
                     <cell>282</cell>
                     <cell>288</cell>
                     <cell>294</cell>
                     <cell>300</cell>
                     <cell>306</cell>
                     <cell>312</cell>
                     <cell>318</cell>
                     <cell>324</cell>
                     <cell>330</cell>
                     <cell>336</cell>
                     <cell>342</cell>
                     <cell>348</cell>
                     <cell>354</cell>
                     <cell>360</cell>
                     <cell>366</cell>
                     <cell>372</cell>
                     <cell>378</cell>
                     <cell>384</cell>
                     <cell>390</cell>
                     <cell>396</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>238</cell>
                     <cell>245</cell>
                     <cell>252</cell>
                     <cell>259</cell>
                     <cell>266</cell>
                     <cell>273</cell>
                     <cell>280</cell>
                     <cell>287</cell>
                     <cell>294</cell>
                     <cell>301</cell>
                     <cell>308</cell>
                     <cell>315</cell>
                     <cell>322</cell>
                     <cell>329</cell>
                     <cell>336</cell>
                     <cell>343</cell>
                     <cell>350</cell>
                     <cell>357</cell>
                     <cell>364</cell>
                     <cell>371</cell>
                     <cell>378</cell>
                     <cell>385</cell>
                     <cell>392</cell>
                     <cell>399</cell>
                     <cell>406</cell>
                     <cell>413</cell>
                     <cell>420</cell>
                     <cell>427</cell>
                     <cell>434</cell>
                     <cell>441</cell>
                     <cell>448</cell>
                     <cell>455</cell>
                     <cell>462</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>272</cell>
                     <cell>280</cell>
                     <cell>288</cell>
                     <cell>296</cell>
                     <cell>304</cell>
                     <cell>312</cell>
                     <cell>320</cell>
                     <cell>328</cell>
                     <cell>336</cell>
                     <cell>344</cell>
                     <cell>352</cell>
                     <cell>360</cell>
                     <cell>368</cell>
                     <cell>376</cell>
                     <cell>384</cell>
                     <cell>392</cell>
                     <cell>400</cell>
                     <cell>408</cell>
                     <cell>416</cell>
                     <cell>424</cell>
                     <cell>432</cell>
                     <cell>440</cell>
                     <cell>448</cell>
                     <cell>456</cell>
                     <cell>464</cell>
                     <cell>472</cell>
                     <cell>480</cell>
                     <cell>488</cell>
                     <cell>496</cell>
                     <cell>504</cell>
                     <cell>512</cell>
                     <cell>520</cell>
                     <cell>528</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>306</cell>
                     <cell>315</cell>
                     <cell>324</cell>
                     <cell>333</cell>
                     <cell>342</cell>
                     <cell>351</cell>
                     <cell>360</cell>
                     <cell>369</cell>
                     <cell>378</cell>
                     <cell>387</cell>
                     <cell>396</cell>
                     <cell>405</cell>
                     <cell>414</cell>
                     <cell>423</cell>
                     <cell>432</cell>
                     <cell>441</cell>
                     <cell>450</cell>
                     <cell>459</cell>
                     <cell>468</cell>
                     <cell>477</cell>
                     <cell>486</cell>
                     <cell>495</cell>
                     <cell>504</cell>
                     <cell>513</cell>
                     <cell>522</cell>
                     <cell>531</cell>
                     <cell>540</cell>
                     <cell>549</cell>
                     <cell>558</cell>
                     <cell>567</cell>
                     <cell>576</cell>
                     <cell>585</cell>
                     <cell>594</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>67</cell>
                     <cell>68</cell>
                     <cell>69</cell>
                     <cell>70</cell>
                     <cell>71</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                     <cell>73</cell>
                     <cell>74</cell>
                     <cell>75</cell>
                     <cell>76</cell>
                     <cell>77</cell>
                     <cell>78</cell>
                     <cell>79</cell>
                     <cell>80</cell>
                     <cell>81</cell>
                     <cell>82</cell>
                     <cell>83</cell>
                     <cell>84</cell>
                     <cell>85</cell>
                     <cell>86</cell>
                     <cell>87</cell>
                     <cell>88</cell>
                     <cell>89</cell>
                     <cell>90</cell>
                     <cell>91</cell>
                     <cell>92</cell>
                     <cell>93</cell>
                     <cell>94</cell>
                     <cell>95</cell>
                     <cell>96</cell>
                     <cell>97</cell>
                     <cell>98</cell>
                     <cell>99</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>134</cell>
                     <cell>136</cell>
                     <cell>138</cell>
                     <cell>140</cell>
                     <cell>142</cell>
                     <cell>144</cell>
                     <cell>146</cell>
                     <cell>148</cell>
                     <cell>150</cell>
                     <cell>152</cell>
                     <cell>154</cell>
                     <cell>156</cell>
                     <cell>158</cell>
                     <cell>160</cell>
                     <cell>162</cell>
                     <cell>164</cell>
                     <cell>166</cell>
                     <cell>168</cell>
                     <cell>170</cell>
                     <cell>172</cell>
                     <cell>174</cell>
                     <cell>176</cell>
                     <cell>178</cell>
                     <cell>180</cell>
                     <cell>182</cell>
                     <cell>184</cell>
                     <cell>186</cell>
                     <cell>188</cell>
                     <cell>190</cell>
                     <cell>192</cell>
                     <cell>194</cell>
                     <cell>196</cell>
                     <cell>198</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>201</cell>
                     <cell>204</cell>
                     <cell>207</cell>
                     <cell>210</cell>
                     <cell>213</cell>
                     <cell>216</cell>
                     <cell>219</cell>
                     <cell>222</cell>
                     <cell>225</cell>
                     <cell>228</cell>
                     <cell>231</cell>
                     <cell>234</cell>
                     <cell>237</cell>
                     <cell>240</cell>
                     <cell>243</cell>
                     <cell>246</cell>
                     <cell>249</cell>
                     <cell>252</cell>
                     <cell>255</cell>
                     <cell>258</cell>
                     <cell>261</cell>
                     <cell>264</cell>
                     <cell>267</cell>
                     <cell>270</cell>
                     <cell>273</cell>
                     <cell>276</cell>
                     <cell>279</cell>
                     <cell>282</cell>
                     <cell>285</cell>
                     <cell>288</cell>
                     <cell>291</cell>
                     <cell>294</cell>
                     <cell>297</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>268</cell>
                     <cell>272</cell>
                     <cell>276</cell>
                     <cell>280</cell>
                     <cell>284</cell>
                     <cell>288</cell>
                     <cell>292</cell>
                     <cell>296</cell>
                     <cell>300</cell>
                     <cell>304</cell>
                     <cell>308</cell>
                     <cell>312</cell>
                     <cell>316</cell>
                     <cell>320</cell>
                     <cell>324</cell>
                     <cell>328</cell>
                     <cell>332</cell>
                     <cell>336</cell>
                     <cell>340</cell>
                     <cell>344</cell>
                     <cell>348</cell>
                     <cell>352</cell>
                     <cell>356</cell>
                     <cell>360</cell>
                     <cell>364</cell>
                     <cell>368</cell>
                     <cell>372</cell>
                     <cell>376</cell>
                     <cell>380</cell>
                     <cell>384</cell>
                     <cell>388</cell>
                     <cell>392</cell>
                     <cell>396</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>335</cell>
                     <cell>340</cell>
                     <cell>345</cell>
                     <cell>350</cell>
                     <cell>355</cell>
                     <cell>360</cell>
                     <cell>365</cell>
                     <cell>370</cell>
                     <cell>375</cell>
                     <cell>380</cell>
                     <cell>385</cell>
                     <cell>390</cell>
                     <cell>395</cell>
                     <cell>400</cell>
                     <cell>405</cell>
                     <cell>410</cell>
                     <cell>415</cell>
                     <cell>420</cell>
                     <cell>425</cell>
                     <cell>430</cell>
                     <cell>435</cell>
                     <cell>440</cell>
                     <cell>445</cell>
                     <cell>450</cell>
                     <cell>455</cell>
                     <cell>460</cell>
                     <cell>465</cell>
                     <cell>470</cell>
                     <cell>475</cell>
                     <cell>480</cell>
                     <cell>485</cell>
                     <cell>490</cell>
                     <cell>495</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>402</cell>
                     <cell>408</cell>
                     <cell>414</cell>
                     <cell>420</cell>
                     <cell>426</cell>
                     <cell>432</cell>
                     <cell>438</cell>
                     <cell>444</cell>
                     <cell>450</cell>
                     <cell>456</cell>
                     <cell>462</cell>
                     <cell>468</cell>
                     <cell>474</cell>
                     <cell>480</cell>
                     <cell>486</cell>
                     <cell>492</cell>
                     <cell>498</cell>
                     <cell>504</cell>
                     <cell>510</cell>
                     <cell>516</cell>
                     <cell>522</cell>
                     <cell>528</cell>
                     <cell>534</cell>
                     <cell>540</cell>
                     <cell>546</cell>
                     <cell>552</cell>
                     <cell>558</cell>
                     <cell>564</cell>
                     <cell>570</cell>
                     <cell>576</cell>
                     <cell>582</cell>
                     <cell>588</cell>
                     <cell>594</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>469</cell>
                     <cell>476</cell>
                     <cell>483</cell>
                     <cell>490</cell>
                     <cell>497</cell>
                     <cell>504</cell>
                     <cell>511</cell>
                     <cell>518</cell>
                     <cell>525</cell>
                     <cell>532</cell>
                     <cell>539</cell>
                     <cell>546</cell>
                     <cell>553</cell>
                     <cell>560</cell>
                     <cell>567</cell>
                     <cell>574</cell>
                     <cell>581</cell>
                     <cell>588</cell>
                     <cell>595</cell>
                     <cell>602</cell>
                     <cell>609</cell>
                     <cell>616</cell>
                     <cell>623</cell>
                     <cell>630</cell>
                     <cell>637</cell>
                     <cell>644</cell>
                     <cell>651</cell>
                     <cell>658</cell>
                     <cell>665</cell>
                     <cell>672</cell>
                     <cell>679</cell>
                     <cell>686</cell>
                     <cell>693</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>536</cell>
                     <cell>544</cell>
                     <cell>552</cell>
                     <cell>560</cell>
                     <cell>568</cell>
                     <cell>576</cell>
                     <cell>584</cell>
                     <cell>592</cell>
                     <cell>600</cell>
                     <cell>608</cell>
                     <cell>616</cell>
                     <cell>624</cell>
                     <cell>632</cell>
                     <cell>640</cell>
                     <cell>648</cell>
                     <cell>656</cell>
                     <cell>664</cell>
                     <cell>672</cell>
                     <cell>680</cell>
                     <cell>688</cell>
                     <cell>696</cell>
                     <cell>704</cell>
                     <cell>712</cell>
                     <cell>720</cell>
                     <cell>728</cell>
                     <cell>736</cell>
                     <cell>744</cell>
                     <cell>752</cell>
                     <cell>760</cell>
                     <cell>768</cell>
                     <cell>776</cell>
                     <cell>784</cell>
                     <cell>792</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>603</cell>
                     <cell>612</cell>
                     <cell>621</cell>
                     <cell>630</cell>
                     <cell>639</cell>
                     <cell>648</cell>
                     <cell>657</cell>
                     <cell>666</cell>
                     <cell>675</cell>
                     <cell>684</cell>
                     <cell>693</cell>
                     <cell>702</cell>
                     <cell>711</cell>
                     <cell>720</cell>
                     <cell>729</cell>
                     <cell>738</cell>
                     <cell>747</cell>
                     <cell>756</cell>
                     <cell>765</cell>
                     <cell>774</cell>
                     <cell>783</cell>
                     <cell>792</cell>
                     <cell>801</cell>
                     <cell>810</cell>
                     <cell>819</cell>
                     <cell>828</cell>
                     <cell>837</cell>
                     <cell>846</cell>
                     <cell>855</cell>
                     <cell>864</cell>
                     <cell>873</cell>
                     <cell>882</cell>
                     <cell>891</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60664:30"/>
               <table>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Figure.</hi> 1</head>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>A</cell>
                     <cell cols="7"> </cell>
                     <cell>B</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                     <cell>49</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                     <cell>81</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fig.</hi> 2</head>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>S. 1</cell>
                     <cell>C. 01</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>08</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>125</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>216</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>49</cell>
                     <cell>343</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                     <cell>512</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>81</cell>
                     <cell>729</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fig.</hi> 3</head>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>A</cell>
                     <cell cols="7"> </cell>
                     <cell>B</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                     <cell>49</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                     <cell>81</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fig.</hi> 4</head>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>S. 1</cell>
                     <cell>C. 01</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>08</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>125</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>216</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>49</cell>
                     <cell>343</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                     <cell>512</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>81</cell>
                     <cell>729</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>numerical table too complicated to transcribe</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fig.</hi> 5</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>numerical table too complicated to transcribe</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fig.</hi> 6</head>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>numerical table too complicated to transcribe</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fig.</hi> 7</head>
               </figure>
               <table>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fig.</hi> 8</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>12</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*24</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*36</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>34</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*68</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*102</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*48</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*60</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*72</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>136</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>170</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>204</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*84</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*96</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>108</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>238</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>272</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>306</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fig.</hi> 9</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>123</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*246</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*369</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*492</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*615</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*738</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*861</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*984</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1107</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fig.</hi> 10</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1̇2̇3̇4̇</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*2468</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*3702</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*4936</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*6170</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*7404</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*8638</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0872</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>11106</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fig.</hi> 11</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>S. 1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*4</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*9</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>C. 01</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*08</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*27</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>00</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>000</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*000</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*000</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>16</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>25</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>36</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*64</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>125</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>216</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*000</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*000</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*000</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>49</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>64</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>81</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>343</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>512</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>729</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*000</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*000</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*000</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fig.</hi> 12</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>78,96,78</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>78,96,7,8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>78,9,67,8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>7,8,9,67,8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>7,8,96,78</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>7,8,9,6,78</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>54,72,54 72</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>54,72,5,4,7,2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>54,7,25,4,72</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>5,47,25,4,72</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>5,4,7,2,54,72</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fig.</hi> 13</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>  1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>* 2 4 6 9 1 3 5 7 8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>* 3 7 0 3 7 0 3 0 7</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>* 4 9 3 8 2 7 1 5 6</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>* 6 1 7 2 8 3 9 4 5</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>* 7 4 0 7 4 0 7 3 4</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>* 8 6 4 1 9 7 5 2 3</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>* 9 8 7 0 5 4 3 1 2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 0 1.</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fig.</hi> 14</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*222</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*333</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*444</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*666</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*666</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>999</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>888</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>132</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>110</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>165</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>132</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>198</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>154</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>231</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>176</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>264</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>198</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>297</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*444</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*555</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*008</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*888</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>110</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>132</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>132</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>165</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>108</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>170</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>220</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>204</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>220</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>27<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>330</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>204</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>330</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>396</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>3108</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>385</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>402</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>352</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>440</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>5328</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>300</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>405</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>504</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*777</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*888</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*999</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>154</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>176</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>198</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>231</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>264</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>297</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>3108</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>352</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>396</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>385</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>440</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>495</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>462</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>5328</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>594</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>5439</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>0210</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>693</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>6216</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>7104</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>792</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>693</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>792</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>891</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fig.</hi> 15</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>Sq. 1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*4</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*9</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>C. 01</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*08</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*27</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>16</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>25</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>36</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*64</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>125</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>216</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>49</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>64</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>81</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>343</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>512</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>729</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*0</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>*00</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60664:30"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60664:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
